Guide to the Time Inc. Corporate Editorial Records 1944-2003 (bulk 1959-1994) MS 3009-RG 6
New-York Historical Society
Time Inc. Corporate Editorial Records
1944-2003
1959-1994
New-York Historical Society
Time, inc.
MS 3009-RG 6
200.75 Linear feet in 201 record cartons
The Corporate Editorial Records contain records from editorial staff working at the corporate level overseeing all publications at Time Inc. This includes the editor-in-chief, editorial director, corporate editor, assistant corporate editor, development editor, and special assistant.
Arrangement
Organized into five series based on hierarchy of job titles and then chronologically by office holder with general office files at the end of the job title:
Series I. Editor-in-Chief Files
Series II. Editorial Director Files
Series III. Corporate Editor Files
Series IV. Assistant Corporate Editor Files
Series V. Development Editor Files
Series VI. Special Assistant to the Editor-in-Chief Files
Historical Note
The office of Editor-in-Chief did not exist at the formation of Time Inc. since the company initially had only Time as its major publication. Cofounders Henry R. Luce and Briton Hadden were both listed on the Time masthead as editors from 1923 through Hadden's death in 1929. Though both were listed, their agreement in practice was to swap positions as the heads of editorial and business.
After Hadden's death, John S. Martin became the managing editor of Time with Luce listed above him as editor. According to Robert T. Elson, writer of the authorized history of Time Inc., Luce was using the title of editor-in-chief in 1938 when he resigned as Time Inc.'s president and chief operating officer, but retained his roles as board chairman and editor-in-chief.
According to Time Inc.'s history on the company intranet, Luce restructured the management of the magazines in 1937, giving each a publisher, a managing editor, and an advertising director. This restructuring established the separation of the business side from the editorial side, respectively referred to as church and state by staff. Luce formalized these roles and the importance of separating them in a 1938 memo entitled "The Principles, Policies, Attitudes Etc. Which Govern and Motivate Time Inc." It is possible this restructuring is when Luce took on the title Editor-in-Chief although he isn't listed as such on magazine mastheads or in the annual reports until the 1940s. According to the intranet, Luce wrote a note to Hedley Donovan, his pick for next editor-in-chief, in 1962 reiterating the necessity of the independence of the office.
Editor-in-Chief was the top editorial position at Time Inc., overseeing editorial policies and standards for all titles and divisions including magazines, books and newspapers. The entire editorial side reported up to this position, and the editor-in-chief reported directly to the board. The publishing/business side reported up to top business executive which became the chief executive officer around 1960. In 1978, shortly before his retirement, Donovan presented a statement to the board to precisely define the role of editor-in-chief so that the office would be preserved for future holders. This statement was formally adopted as company policy in December 1978. In April 1986, succeeding Editor-in-Chief Henry Grunwald further updated the definition of the title in a statement to the board, a copy of which is in Ray Cave's files.
After the merger of Time Inc. and Warner Communications in 1990 when the magazine and books divisions became subsidiaries, the editor-in-chief began reporting to the head of Time Warner blurring the editorial and publishing/business separation. In 2014 when Time Inc. disaffiliated from Time Warner, the editor-in-chief was replaced by the chief content officer reporting to the chief executive officer which removed the separation altogether.
Citations:
Bill Hooper, email to Holly Deakyne, 10 June 2016.
Bill Hooper, email to Holly Deakyne, 8 May 2017.
Prendergast, Curtis, and Geoffrey Colvin. 1986. The World of Time Inc.: The Intimate History of a Changing Enterprise, 1960-1980. New York: Atheneum.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers with the exception of restricted materials. Restricted materials may include privileged attorney correspondence; student records; medical records; personnel performance evaluations; contracts and agreements; records with personally identifiable information; and sealed court records. Restricted materials are located in boxes R9, R10, R12-R14, R17-R19, and R23. Materials created within the past 35 years also may be subject to restriction on a case-by-case basis.
Unreformatted audiovisual and digital material in the collection is not accessible.
Materials are stored offsite and advance notice is required for use.
Related Archival Materials Note
This finding aid relates to just one record group of the Time Inc. Records. For information about the other record groups and for overall information about the archives, please see the Guide to the Time Inc. Records (MS 3009). The Henry Luce Papers (MS 3014) were acquired with the Time Inc. Records. The collection of books acquired with the records are cataloged as the Time Inc. Reference Library.
Related records outside of the New-York Historical Society include:
Hedley Donovan papers, University Archives, University of Minnesota, Twin Cities.
Henry A. Grunwald papers, Library of Congress Manuscript Division Washington, D.C., https://lccn.loc.gov/mm2005085225.
Scope and Contents Note
The Corporate Editorial Records contain records from editorial staff working at the corporate level. This includes the editor-in-chief, editorial director, corporate editor, assistant corporate editor, development editor, and special assistant. These positions oversaw editorial work on all publications at Time Inc. Executive offices, including the top editorial staff, were located on the 34th floor in the Time & Life Building, and many folder titles and records reference the "34th floor" as shorthand for the corporate offices.
Records for some staff includes material from prior positions, mainly in the editorial offices of Time magazine.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Time Inc. in 2015.
Appointment books; Corporation records.; Corporations -- History.; Corporations -- New York (State) -- New York.; Editors -- New York (State) -- New York.; Organization files.; Publishers and publishing -- New York (State) -- New York.; Speeches (documents); Cave, Ray, 1929-; Donovan, Hedley; Gaines, James R.; Graves, Ralph, 1924-2013; Grunwald, Henry A. (Henry Anatole); Korn, Jerry; Loeb, Marshall; Lubar, Robert, -1995; Maness, David; McManus, Jason, 1934-; Nicholas, N. J., Jr. (Nicholas J.), approximately 1940-; Rogin, Gilbert, 1929-2017; Stolley, Richard B.; Time, inc. -- Archives.; Time, inc. -- History.; Time, inc. -- Management.
- Series I.A. Editor-in-Chief Hedley Donovan Files, 1948-1989 (bulk 1959-1979); 56.5 Linear feet in 57 record cartons
  Biographical Note
  Hedley Donovan was the second editor-in-chief of Time Inc. from 1964 to 1979, a position previously held only by the company's cofounder Henry R. Luce.
  Donovan was a native of Minnesota and after graduating from the University of Minnesota, he spent three years at Oxford University studying history on a Rhodes scholarship. Instead of accepting a Harvard teaching assistant position, after graduation Donovan took the better paying job as a reporter at the Washington Post working on general and political assignments. During World War II, he served in Naval Intelligence.
  Fortune hired Donovan as a writer in 1945, promoting him to associate managing editor around 1950 and managing editor by 1953. In July 1959, Time Inc. announced Donovan's new position as editorial director, a deputy position to the editor-in-chief. While editorial director, Donovan established the Research and Development unit to conduct studies regarding Time Inc.'s ventures in television programming. In 1962, he was named to the board of directors. When Luce retired in April 1964, he recommended that the board appoint Donovan as his replacement.
  During his tenure as editor-in-chief, Donovan made the decision to suspend publishing of Life in 1972 for financial reasons and launched the magazines Money (1972) and People (1974). Under his supervision, the Magazine Development Group also considered other new magazine ideas: Well, regarding health topics; Camera Month; View, the description of which sounds like a precursor to People; and a women's magazine. Though the women's magazine received a title (Woman), and several years of work went into it, it was never realized. Time Inc. also acquired the Washington Star newspaper near the end of Donovan's tenure.
  In 1978, shortly before his retirement, Donovan presented a statement to the board to precisely define the role of editor-in-chief so that the office would be preserved for future holders. As transcribed in Prendergast and Colvin's book The World of Time Inc.: The Intimate History of a Changing Enterprise, 1960-1980, he stated: "[The editor-in-chief] is responsible solely to the board for editorial content." "The board... delegates to the editor-in-chief the continuing appraisal and direction of the company's editorial work." "The editor-in-chief is a member of the board and of its executive committee." "The board does not expect the editor-in-chief to maintain the same immediate authority over the editorial work of Books and the [Washington] Star as he does over the magazines. He will, however, appoint the managing editor of Books and the editor of the Star..."
  His statement also defined the relationship of the editorial director as senior deputy to the editor-in-chief. This statement was formally adopted as company policy in December 1978.
  While preparing for retirement, Donovan recommended his replacement be Henry Grunwald with Ralph Graves as the editorial director. Donovan retired as editor-in-chief in June 1979. F.Y.I., the Time Inc. staff newsletter published a special issue of articles about Donovan on June 4, 1979. Though officially retired from Time Inc., Donovan remained a consultant until at least 1985.
  After Donovan's retirement, he wanted to take some of his files in order to write his memoirs. Two sets of copies were made, one for the Archives and one for the researchers and writers working on the history of Time Inc. book. The original materials may be in the papers Donovan's family donated to the University Archives at the University of Minnesota, Twin Cities.
  Beginning in July 1979, Donovan served approximately one year as a White House senior advisor to President Jimmy Carter. In 1981, he was the visiting journalist at Harvard University, and in 1989 Donovan published his memoirs Right Places, Right Times: Forty Years in Journalism, Not Counting My Paper Route.
  Citations:
  Elson, Robert T. 1968. Time Inc.: The Intimate History of a Publishing Enterprise, 1923-1941. New York: Atheneum.
  Elson, Robert T., and Duncan Norton-Taylor. 1973. The World of Time Inc.: The Intimate History of a Publishing Enterprise, 1941-1960. New York: Atheneum.
  Bill Hooper, email to Holly Deakyne, 22 February 2017.
  Jimmy Carter: "Senior Adviser to the President Appointment of Hedley W. Donovan.," July 25, 1979. Online by Gerhard Peters and John T. Woolley, The American Presidency Project. http://www.presidency.ucsb.edu/ws/?pid=32649.
  Prendergast, Curtis, and Geoffrey Colvin. 1986. The World of Time Inc.: The Intimate History of a Changing Enterprise, 1960-1980. New York: Atheneum.
  Scope and Contents Note
  The Hedley Donovan Files contain the files kept by his office while he was editorial director and editor-in-chief. The files also include some records or copies of records up to four years after his retirement. The files document his schedule, professional expenses, collected research reports, speeches, office subject files, travel, and draft memoirs.
  Arrangement Note
  Organized into seven subseries:
  Subseries I.A.1. Appointment Books
  Subseries I.A.2. Expense Reports
  Subseries I.A.3. Research and Development Reports
  Subseries I.A.4. Speeches, Lectures, and Presentations
  Subseries I.A.5. Subject Files
  Subseries I.A.6. Trips
  Subseries I.A.7. Audiovisual
  Subseries I.A.8. Personal
  - Subseries I.A.1. Appointment Books, 1959-1978; 6 Linear feet in 6 record cartons
    The Appointment Books document Donovan Hedley's schedule, professional and personal, and many of the years contain multiple books. As some are marked "T. Lanz," these are probably the books of his schedule kept by his executive secretary Gertrude "Trudi" Lanz. Some are marked with "Mrs. Donovan" indicating they are his wife Dorothy Donovan's schedule. Books similar in appearance to the marked books are tentatively attributed to her. A few of the books from 1973 were removed from a tax audit accordion folder that also contained expense reports.
    Organized chronologically.
    - Appointment Books, 1959-1962 (Offsite-box 715)
    - Appointment Books, 1962-1966 (Offsite-box 716)
    - Appointment Books, 1967-1970 (Offsite-box 717)
    - Appointment Books, 1971-1973 (Offsite-box 718)
    - Appointment Books, 1973-1975 (Offsite-box 719)
    - Appointment Books, 1976-1978 (Offsite-box 720, Folder 1-5)
  - Subseries I.A.2. Expense Reports, 1953-1977; 2 Linear feet in 2 record cartons (Offsite-box 720-721)
    Expense Reports contain Hedley Donovan's reported expenses for his corporate account. Some reports from 1973 were removed from a tax audit accordion folder which also contained appointment books.
  - Subseries I.A.3. Research and Development Reports, 1962-1979; 5 Linear feet in 5 record cartons
    Research and Development Reports contains reports from various staff regarding their research into new areas for Time Inc. such as the role of the magazine in culture, educational texts, audio-visual media, newspaper publishing, and new magazines.
    Organized chronologically with general folders at the front.
    - Transfer to Archives Form, 1979 (Offsite-box 721, Folder 11)
    - General, 1962-1969 (Offsite-box 721, Folder 12-16)
    - Inventory, 1964-1966 (Offsite-box 721, Folder 17)
    - Pay Television, 1962-1968 (Offsite-box 721, Folder 18-19)
    - Television Program Suggestions: Henry Grunwald: March 1963 (Offsite-box 721, Folder 20)
    - Report on Television: Henry Grunwald: March 1963 (Offsite-box 722, Folder 1)
    - Role of the Mass Magazine in U.S. Society: Rhett Austell: April 1963 (Offsite-box 722, Folder 2)
    - The Role of Mass Magazine in U.S. Society: Rhett Austell and Henry Grunwald: June 1963 (Offsite-box 722, Folder 3)
    - Travel Magazine: July 1963 (Offsite-box 722, Folder 4)
    - Evaluation of Pay TV Systems: Volume I: Executive Summary: Arthur D. Little, Inc.: August 1963 (Offsite-box 722, Folder 5)
    - TV: August 1963 (Offsite-box 722, Folder 6)
    - Expected Changes in Mass Communications: Spindletop Research: September 1963 (Offsite-box 722, Folder 7)
    - Changes in America, 1963 (Offsite-box 722, Folder 8-9)
    - Life: Outside Critiques, 1963 (Offsite-box 722, Folder 10)
    - Silberman Education Project, 1963-1965 (Offsite-box 722, Folder 11-12)
    - Silberman Appendices, undated (Offsite-box 722, Folder 13)
    - Encyclopedia Study, 1963-1968 (Offsite-box 722, Folder 14)
    - Sporting Events Program: April 1964 (Offsite-box 722, Folder 15)
    - Education and the New Role of Knowledge: Charles E. Silberman: May 1964 (Offsite-box 722, Folder 16)
    - Famous Artists Schools, Inc.: August 1964 (Offsite-box 723, Folder 1)
    - Education: Charles Silberman: October 1964 (Offsite-box 723, Folder 2)
    - Adult Education: Martha R. Wallace: November 1964 (Offsite-box 723, Folder 3)
    - Book Div: Education R&D Report: November 1964 (Offsite-box 723, Folder 4)
    - Audiovisual Survey: Earl E. Welch: December 1964 (Offsite-box 723, Folder 5)
    - Culture Magazine: Max Ways, 1964 (Offsite-box 723, Folder 6)
    - Del Pain, 1964 (Offsite-box 723, Folder 7)
    - Distribution List: 1964?, undated (Offsite-box 723, Folder 8)
    - Itex, 1964-1965 (Offsite-box 723, Folder 9)
    - Time-Life Books: Educational: Nine-Month Report: January 1965 (Offsite-box 723, Folder 10)
    - A Magazine About Innovation: Max Ways: April 1965 (Offsite-box 723, Folder 11)
    - Report on International Publishing: Charles L. Gleason and Curtis Prendergast: June 1965 (Offsite-box 723, Folder 12)
    - Time-Life Books: Educational: Audio-Visual: June 1965 (Offsite-box 723, Folder 13)
    - Time Inc. GE Study: Roger Egan: July? 1965 (Offsite-box 723, Folder 14)
    - Markets for Educational Material Abroad: Alex Groner: September 1965 (Offsite-box 724, Folder 1)
    - Travel Magazines: Ruth Mehrtens: December 1965 (Offsite-box 724, Folder 2)
    - Australia-New Zealand News Section to Time South Pacific, 1965 (Offsite-box 724, Folder 3)
    - Luce, Hank, 1965 (Offsite-box 724, Folder 4)
    - Wootton, Phil, 1965-1968 (Offsite-box 724, Folder 5)
    - Newspapers, 1965-1969 (Offsite-box 724, Folder 6-7)
    - Report on Daily Newspaper Business: Nick Nicholas: September 1966 (Offsite-box 724, Folder 8)
    - Information Technology: Putney Westerfield and Martha Wallace: October 1966 (Offsite-box 724, Folder 9)
    - Wallace, Martha: Memo: "The Moving Image" and Baker Memo, 1966-1967 (Offsite-box 724, Folder 10)
    - Planning Data in the Information Utility Field: Markets and Services: Volume Two: The Diebold Group, Inc.: February 1967 (Offsite-box 724, Folder 11)
    - Planning Data in the Information Utility Field: Markets and Services: Volume Three: Diebold: February 1967 (Offsite-box 724, Folder 12)
    - Information Utilities as a New Business Opportunity: Volume One: The Diebold Group, Inc.: March 1967 (Offsite-box 724-725)
    - Newspapers: Need and Opportunity for Time Inc.: Marshall Loeb: October 1967 (Offsite-box 725, Folder 2-3)
    - Business Development at Time Inc./Technical Development at Time Inc.: February 1968 (Offsite-box 725, Folder 4)
    - Where Magazine: September 1968 (Offsite-box 725, Folder 5)
    - Time-Life News: Wire Service, 1969 (Offsite-box 725, Folder 6)
    - Management Compensation Study, 1970 (Offsite-box 725, Folder 7)
    - A Study of Newspaper Publishing: Nancy G. McNulty, 1972 (Offsite-box 725, Folder 8)
  - Subseries I.A.4. Speeches, Lectures, and Presentations, 1954-1981; 2 Linear feet in 2 record cartons
    Speeches, Lectures, and Presentations contains invitations, correspondence, memoranda, notes, itineraries and other records regarding speeches, lectures and presentations by Hedley Donovan. All are duplicated files, but not all of the materials are copies created by the Time Inc. Archives. The files include some original copies, extra copies, carbon copies, and a very few original items.
    Arrangement
    - 1954 October 27: HD Speech: Minneapolis (Offsite-box 725, Folder 9)
    - 1956 January 31: Speech: Poor Richard, Philadelphia (Offsite-box 725, Folder 10)
    - 1956 May 9: Advertising Sales: Ponte Vedra (Offsite-box 725, Folder 11)
    - 1956 May: Minnesota Alumni Association (Offsite-box 725, Folder 12)
    - 1957 May: Speech Sales Convention: Bermuda (Offsite-box 725, Folder 13)
    - 1958 May 7: World Affairs Center Re: Russia (Offsite-box 725, Folder 14)
    - 1958 May 20: Congressional Church of Manhasset (Offsite-box 725, Folder 15)
    - 1958 May 27: Overseas Press Club Re: Russia (Offsite-box 725, Folder 16)
    - 1958 August 28: Delta Upsilon: On Russia Trip (Offsite-box 725, Folder 17)
    - 1958: Church Group Talk (Offsite-box 725, Folder 18)
    - 1960 April 24: Life Sales Convention (Offsite-box 725, Folder 19)
    - 1960 August 26: National Scholastic Press Association (Offsite-box 725, Folder 20)
    - 1961 March 21: Chicago (Offsite-box 725, Folder 21)
    - 1961 April 10: Washington (Offsite-box 725, Folder 22)
    - 1962 Spring: Speech to TLI Salesmen (Offsite-box 725, Folder 23)
    - 1963 February 1: University of Minnesota Short Course for Working Journalists (Offsite-box 725, Folder 24)
    - 1963 March 18: Sports Illustrated Advertising Sales Convention: Grand Bahama (Offsite-box 725, Folder 25)
    - 1963 October 22: Silver Burdett Dinner: Morris County Golf Club, Morristown, NJ (Offsite-box 725, Folder 26)
    - 1964 May 25: Luce-Donovan Dinner: New York Hilton (Offsite-box 725, Folder 27)
    - 1965 January 18: Sports Illustrated Dinner: Hotel Plaza (Offsite-box 725, Folder 28)
    - 1965 February 23: Foreign Policy Association: New York (Offsite-box 725, Folder 29)
    - 1965 March 4: University of Minnesota Convocation: Minneapolis (Offsite-box 725, Folder 30)
    - 1965 April 21: Yale Daily News Banquet: Yale University, New Haven (Offsite-box 725, Folder 31)
    - 1965 September 29: The Chicago Committee for the Center for the Study of Democratic Institutions (Offsite-box 725, Folder 32)
    - 1965 October 18: Fortune Dinner Honoring Norton-Taylor, Davenport, and Ways: New York (Offsite-box 725, Folder 33)
    - 1965 December 1: Business Outlook Conference: University of Washington Seattle (Offsite-box 725, Folder 34)
    - 1966 March 9: Paul D. Schreiber High School: Port Washington, NY (Offsite-box 725, Folder 35)
    - 1966 June 5: "The Chances of Being Yourself", Commencement Address: Pomona College, Claremont, CA (Offsite-box 725, Folder 36)
    - 1966 October 13: "The Intellectuals and the President" Bell Lecture: Boston University (Offsite-box 725, Folder 37)
    - 1966 November 13: On Eastern Europe Trip to Pillsbury Fellows of University of Minnesota: Minneapolis (Offsite-box 725, Folder 38)
    - 1967 January 11: Congregational Church of Manhasset (Offsite-box 725, Folder 39)
    - 1967 April 8: Impact Symposium: Vanderbilt (Offsite-box 725, Folder 40)
    - 1967 June 5: Commencement Address: Southwestern at Memphis (Offsite-box 725, Folder 41)
    - 1967 June 13: Commencement Address: New York University (Offsite-box 725, Folder 42)
    - 1967 June 13: Letters Commenting, Commencement Address: NYU (Offsite-box 725, Folder 43)
    - 1967 June 13: Notes and Comments, Commencement Address: NYU (Offsite-box 725, Folder 44)
    - 1967 November 3-5: Writer-Editor Conference: Mount Holyoke (Offsite-box 725, Folder 45)
    - 1968 January 11: Chicago-MPA (Offsite-box 725, Folder 46)
    - 1968 April 5-6: Omicron Delta Kappa: Atlanta (Offsite-box 725, Folder 47)
    - 1968 April 18-19: Adcraft Club Speech: Detroit (Offsite-box 725, Folder 48)
    - 1968 April 23-26: Lake Forest Convocation: Chicago (Offsite-box 725, Folder 49)
    - 1968 May: Lake Forest Generation Gap: Mailing to College Presidents (Offsite-box 725, Folder 50)
    - 1968 June 2: Commencement: University of Rochester (Offsite-box 725, Folder 51)
    - 1969 January 13-15: A.I.M.E. Council on Foreign Relations: Duluth (Offsite-box 725, Folder 52)
    - 1969 February: Nial Dinner: Cleveland Public Library Center (Offsite-box 725, Folder 53)
    - 1969 May 28: Paul Schreiber High School: Port Washington, NY (Offsite-box 726, Folder 1)
    - 1969 June 9: Commencement Address: Carnegie-Mellon (Offsite-box 726, Folder 2)
    - 1970 February 19: Fortune speech, 40th Anniversary: St Regis, NY (Offsite-box 726, Folder 3)
    - 1970 March 16: U.S. Foreign Policy Committee: Detroit (Offsite-box 726, Folder 4)
    - 1970 March 17: Editors and Managers for Early 70s Distinguished Visitor Series: Minneapolis (Offsite-box 726, Folder 5)
    - 1970 June 6: Commencement: The Hotchkiss School (Offsite-box 726, Folder 6)
    - 1970 November 17: World Wildlife Fund Congress: London (Offsite-box 726, Folder 7)
    - 1970 December 15: Institute of Life Insurance (Offsite-box 726, Folder 8)
    - 1971 February 24: Cornell Caduceus Society (Offsite-box 726, Folder 9)
    - 1971 March: State of Journalism: Columbia (Offsite-box 726, Folder 10)